[SPEAKER_05]: That's the part that's missing, in other words.
[SPEAKER_05]: You have the information, you know that you've read about the Four Noble Truths, you have some recognition of the three characteristics, whichever aspect of the teaching you might want to
[SPEAKER_05]: To focus on, but you're not living in according to it, in accordance with it.
[SPEAKER_05]: You still live.
[SPEAKER_05]: And it says, inside of a sotāpanna, everything that is liable to arise, is liable to cease.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, some people might have heard of this parable.
[SPEAKER_05]: I think it's from the Hindu tradition that says that what you think is a snake is actually a rope.
[SPEAKER_05]: Therefore, your suffering, on account of that snake, is illusory.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's a mistake, because you're deluded.
[SPEAKER_05]: You don't know the ultimate reality.
[SPEAKER_05]: And if you investigate closely, you would realize that that view was implied in most of the modern understandings of what wisdom is.
[SPEAKER_05]: People expect to gain some sort of access to some ultimate hidden reality as a result of their meditation practice.
[SPEAKER_05]: And then, there might be different
[SPEAKER_05]: The point is you conceive the solution to this problem of suffering your life to be this higher reality that you still haven't accessed.
[SPEAKER_05]: So,
[SPEAKER_05]: Is there a problem with that?
[SPEAKER_05]: What's the difference between that and what the Buddha was teaching in the suttas?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, if you're looking for some higher or ultimate reality, you have already turned your back to what is present in front of you.
[SPEAKER_02]: And as a result of that, you will not be able to understand what is actually already taking place just now.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, how are you going to understand the origin of your present suffering, if you keep turning your back towards it?
[SPEAKER_05]: But what if...
[SPEAKER_05]: What if somebody might say, but the things that are present here are irrelevant, because they're not real, so why should I concern myself with them?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, that's about a pernicious view.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right.
[SPEAKER_03]: But why?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, it might also be, maybe not that they're...
[SPEAKER_03]: It might be said that they're, maybe, not just that they're not relevant, but like, you have a distorted perception of them.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like you have dust in your eyes or something, so that we can't trust your perceptions.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you see, to say that things are not real, you're still talking about things.
[SPEAKER_02]: So the things have to be there first.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then you regard them as not real, as opposed to real.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's always of things that you say that they are not real.
[SPEAKER_02]: So that position actually in and of itself already doesn't add up.
[SPEAKER_02]: Something might be illusory, but it doesn't mean that it isn't there.
[SPEAKER_02]: As an illusion, it is still real.
[SPEAKER_02]: And as such, you suffer on account of that.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that suffering is not because those things are illusory.
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, in other words, where the things are illusory or not, is secondary to the fact that you're suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the point, yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: And, eh... the thing is, it might factually give you a sense of release from your suffering.
[SPEAKER_05]: But it's for the wrong reason, because, like you just said, the things were never the problem to begin with.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, it's kind of the... like, it goes very deeply, and it's not just a...
[SPEAKER_05]: It's not just a coarse view of, again, ultimate reality.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's the view of management, in the most general sense.
[SPEAKER_05]: Often, when people have interpersonal problems, or anger against someone, or something like that, they would think the solution is to reinterpret your relationship with that person.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, tell yourself
[SPEAKER_05]: I think that's called in psychology cognitive reframing, which obviously you don't need the Buddha for.
[SPEAKER_05]: Just telling yourself that, you know, this person is whatever.
[SPEAKER_05]: They're doing this to you because...
[SPEAKER_05]: Their childhood was kind of problematic, or maybe they're having a bad day, and through kind of reframing the situation in that sense, you, quote-unquote, escape the suffering.
[SPEAKER_05]: Alternatively, you might escape the suffering by telling yourself, oh, well, all of these are just... all of these situations are just constantly changing processes.
[SPEAKER_05]: There's nothing
[SPEAKER_05]: There's no inherent essence in this.
[SPEAKER_05]: And through kind of repeating that view to yourself, you eventually kind of stop feeling that which was bothering you.
[SPEAKER_05]: But the thing is, as the Buddha said, what is the origin of suffering?
[SPEAKER_05]: Is it the fact that you didn't have the access to this, to these perceptions, desired perceptions?
[SPEAKER_05]: Is that what he said?
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, obviously not.
[SPEAKER_05]: No.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, it's... he said it's craving that's the origin of suffering.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, when is craving there?
[SPEAKER_03]: When is craving there?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, well, craving will always be in relation to something.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mm-hmm.
[SPEAKER_02]: And so, whether the thing is now real or illusory, all that, it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_05]: Mm-hmm.
[SPEAKER_05]: But more specifically, in relation to what is there craving?
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, I would say feeling.
[SPEAKER_05]: Mm-hmm.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_05]: So,
[SPEAKER_05]: In other words, the problem is that when things are unpleasant, in other words, when you haven't still managed to reframe the thing so that you don't feel the pain anymore, you're liable to craving.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, if you have to then re-explain and reframe the thing so that it's not felt as unpleasant anymore, that's like dealing with the secondary result of
[SPEAKER_05]: The symptom, basically, of the illness, rather than the illness itself, which is the fact that when things are unpleasant, it doesn't matter whether they're illusory or not illusory or whatever, your mind is still liable to resist them.
[SPEAKER_05]: Or, when they're pleasant, it's still liable to pray for them.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, yeah, you keep assuming that the problem is with the things in the world or with other people.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whereas, actually, it isn't.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, that's in general sense.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, how then, what is it that you would have to do to free yourself from suffering?
[SPEAKER_05]: If you don't have to prove to yourself that things are not real, clearly there is still some work to be done and there is still understanding to be developed.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, how could we kind of
[SPEAKER_05]: Paint a clear picture of what that understanding is, if it has nothing to do with the things in denying the resistance or saying that there's some hidden kind of perceptual distortion on the level of the contents of those things.
[SPEAKER_05]: What is it that you don't understand, in other words?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, so when the things in the world are allowed to be there, whether it is other people, just whatever, the things of the world, you're not denying that they're there, you're not rationalizing them away by saying it's an illusion, it's a dream, and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just say they are there.
[SPEAKER_02]: You still notice that there is suffering, and now you are asking
[SPEAKER_02]: What is the right way for that suffering to cease?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, so, but specifically in regard to understanding, because, of course, the whole idea is based on the fact that there is ignorance.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, we're not denying that there's ignorance.
[SPEAKER_05]: We're not saying that there's nothing to be attained or something like that.
[SPEAKER_05]: There is a vast lack of understanding there.
[SPEAKER_05]: But it's not on the level of, like, again, pretty much mystical information that you haven't gained.
[SPEAKER_05]: And that if you were to suddenly... That's another wrong view.
[SPEAKER_05]: That, you know, if you... if you...
[SPEAKER_05]: Magically, if you were to kind of get a glimpse of this, all your problems would be immediately resolved.
[SPEAKER_05]: Whereas, the Buddha Sutras clearly say there is no such thing as sudden penetration to knowledge.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's always gradual.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, what is that understanding that's missing?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, can I just kind of butt in with another thought before we try to answer that question?
[SPEAKER_01]: I guess, existentially speaking, even the notion that
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything is false.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, like, everything is an illusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think this is sort of what Ajahn Pascoe is saying.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, um, that is still blaming those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's kind of offloading the understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, I mean, existentially speaking,
[SPEAKER_01]: The appearance of things still belongs to those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if your understanding of understanding depends on these things being otherwise, then that's not really in your control.
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, and for that matter, it's also infinite.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because how do you know
[SPEAKER_05]: That there isn't a more ultimate reality than the one that you're... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, it's... you're just chasing this kind of... you're chasing this thing that you yourself are creating, in other words.
[SPEAKER_05]: And, so...
[SPEAKER_05]: And, I mean, there's many angles you could approach it, but also the suttas would say that, you know, whether it's past, present, future, inferior, superior, coarse or fine, regardless of what it is, all form, all feeling, all perception,
[SPEAKER_05]: All activities, all consciousness must be seen in the same way.
[SPEAKER_05]: In other words, there's nothing special.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, if your view is that by finding something special, you free yourself from suffering.
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, as much as you might want to deny that, you might come up with all these mystical views that, oh, look, this thing that I discovered is outside of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_05]: And that's why it's, quote-unquote, the escape.
[SPEAKER_05]: But all you're doing there is you're failing to apply that blanket recognition that all forms
[SPEAKER_05]: Because it doesn't matter how you spin it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Like, anything that is arisen has to be within those five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, which includes the idea that there might be something outside of the aggregates.
[SPEAKER_05]: It doesn't matter what perception it is, what kind of... Yeah, like the most exalted sense of other-worldly kind of sanctuary from everything.
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, it's felt.
[SPEAKER_05]: You can already see that it's felt, because clearly you regard it as pleasant.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, it's already within the five areas.
[SPEAKER_05]: It doesn't matter what you think.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, ideas or ideals that you are striving after, that is also, right, mental, but it's fully within the aggregates.
[SPEAKER_05]: Even the most, eh...
[SPEAKER_05]: acute experience that you might get at the end of your meditation, it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_05]: It has to be form, feeling, perception, intention, and consciousness.
[SPEAKER_05]: You're completely confined within those things.
[SPEAKER_05]: So,
[SPEAKER_02]: That means that your meditation practice ironically becomes quite real when you adopt that view, but also, in a certain sense, a bit boring, because now all your notions of what is esoteric and special and mystical are going to be within those aggregates.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right?
[SPEAKER_02]: So it just sort of flattens out.
[SPEAKER_02]: So one needs to be prepared that it might actually be somewhat grey, dull and boring, but ironically, that's far more real.
[SPEAKER_05]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because
[SPEAKER_05]: Did you suffer?
[SPEAKER_05]: What was the thing that you were suffering about?
[SPEAKER_05]: What is the ultimate reality?
[SPEAKER_05]: Or was it the mundane kind of pleasure and pain when people were, you know, not doing... as Suttas would often say, when you were separated from things that were dear, united with things that were not dear, sickness, aging, death, bodily displeasure, mental displeasure,
[SPEAKER_05]: Those are the things that you were suffering in regard to.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, why are you going in this completely different direction, that has nothing to do with it, to escape the...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, I don't know, I have some kind of...
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, physical ailment, literally, and my escape is just to take psychedelic mushrooms, to take myself to this completely different dimension, and then I have this magical expectation that I'll be able to keep up that altered state forever, so that I never have to get united with the old things again.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, now, going back to the previous question,
[SPEAKER_05]: If that's not understanding, then, what is the understanding that you develop, such that you don't suffer anymore?
[SPEAKER_05]: Why all the same mundane things are there, because the five aggregates are the mundane?
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, stopping ignoring the fact that, well, that those things are, well, that whatever you perceive,
[SPEAKER_04]: No matter how special, it's still within perception.
[SPEAKER_04]: And no matter what you feel, no matter how pleasant, it's still within feeling.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, how... what would be... what are you trying to achieve by cultivating that understanding, I guess?
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, not resisting the things the way they are.
[SPEAKER_04]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, there's no more magical piece of the puzzle that's missing.
[SPEAKER_05]: Anything more hidden than the fact that when pain is there, you resist it.
[SPEAKER_05]: When pleasure is there, you cannot help yourself but to want more of it.
[SPEAKER_05]: And that's the entire saṃsāra, from the most, kind of, banal, everyday things, to the most subtle, kind of, fetters of immaterial
[SPEAKER_05]: The grounds and all this stuff, the entire thing, is the same thing, just feeling not being understood.
[SPEAKER_05]: And actually, the Buddha said, somebody who understands the three feelings, understands the origin, gratification and... no, the gratification, danger and escape,
[SPEAKER_05]: In regard to the three feelings, he says there is nothing more that they need to do.
[SPEAKER_05]: The work is done and there was no... at no point they abandoned the, quote-unquote, mundane reality, which is precisely those feelings.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, yeah, in other words...
[SPEAKER_05]: The understanding that you have to cultivate is... well, that's actually how he would always phrase it, like gratification, danger and escape.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, you understand why was it that you were passionate towards whatever you were passionate towards.
[SPEAKER_05]: And you understand why it's dangerous to be passionate towards it.
[SPEAKER_05]: And when you fully, completely understand
[SPEAKER_05]: That that passion is like, as Siddhartha would say, putting your head in a chopping block, as we discussed in one of the previous talks.
[SPEAKER_05]: Then, you won't have to wish for the passion not to be there.
[SPEAKER_05]: It will have to go, because the passion was based on you still regarding those things as
[SPEAKER_05]: It's as simple as that.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's not being sufficiently clear about the fact that what you regard as pleasant, it's real as such.
[SPEAKER_05]: There is a pleasant aspect to it, but it comes with this kind of simultaneous danger, peril.
[SPEAKER_05]: Like, eh...
[SPEAKER_05]: I think the sutta also gave a simile that it's like, eh... like a razor blade that is honey smeared all over it.
[SPEAKER_05]: And you can't help yourself but to keep licking it and cutting yourself at the same time.
[SPEAKER_05]: And, eh... and that's all.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, you wouldn't need to... Because, see, actually, it's not just you wouldn't need to go and chase after the ultimate reality.
[SPEAKER_05]: You realize the ultimate reality
[SPEAKER_05]: Isn't ultimate at all.
[SPEAKER_05]: Like, you are kind of defining it as such, because of your assumption, but it still is, as I said before, it still is pleasant, and there is still a gratification there, there is still a danger there, and there is still an escape there, but because you kind of stopped at the content of how special it is, you didn't realize that actually it had to be included within the same exact principle.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, eh...
[SPEAKER_05]: So, appearance is our view.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's all you know.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And in that sense, all there is, is what appears.
[SPEAKER_05]: There's...
[SPEAKER_05]: Appearance is reality, to an extent.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: And actually, speaking about that, there's a sutta where the Buddha kind of alludes to this whole view that things are quote-unquote not real.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's Sankhya 2294.
[SPEAKER_05]: It says, because I do not argue with the world, it is the world that argues with me.
[SPEAKER_05]: One whose speech is in line with the dhamma does not argue with anyone in the world.
[SPEAKER_05]: What the wise deem as not existing, I too say does not exist.
[SPEAKER_05]: What the wise deem as existing, I too say exists.
[SPEAKER_05]: And what do the wise deem as not existing, which I too say does not exist.
[SPEAKER_05]: Form that is permanent, everlasting, eternal, and imperishable.
[SPEAKER_05]: Feeling, perception, activities, consciousness, that is permanent, everlasting, eternal, and imperishable.
[SPEAKER_05]: This is what the wise deem as not existing, which I too say does not exist.
[SPEAKER_05]: And what do the wise deem as existing, which I too say exists?
[SPEAKER_05]: Form that is impermanent, suffering, imperishable.
[SPEAKER_05]: Emphasis on it exists.
[SPEAKER_05]: Feeling, perception, choices.
[SPEAKER_05]: There exists a mundane phenomenon in the world, and that is what the Tathāgata awakens to and comprehends.
[SPEAKER_05]: Having awakened to it and comprehended it, he teaches, asserts, establishes, clarifies, analyzes and reveals it.
[SPEAKER_05]: And what is that mundane phenomenon in the world?
[SPEAKER_05]: Form is a mundane phenomenon in the world, feeling, perception, activities.
[SPEAKER_05]: Consciousness is a mundane phenomenon in the world that the Tathāgata awakens to and comprehends, then he explains, teaches, asserts, establishes, clarifies, analyzes, and reveals it.
[SPEAKER_05]: This being so, what can I do about a foolish, ordinary person, blind and sightless, who does not know and see?
[SPEAKER_05]: Suppose, in other words, somebody who thinks that things don't exist, even though he's clearly saying that there are things that exist.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: Suppose there was a blue water lily or a pink or white lotus.
[SPEAKER_05]: Though it sprouted and grew in the water, it will rise up above the water and stand with no water clinging to it.
[SPEAKER_05]: In the same way, though the Tathāgata has been born and has grown up in the world, he lives having overcome the world, unsullied by the world.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, that simile almost says it all.
[SPEAKER_05]: Like, what is it that makes you be...
[SPEAKER_05]: So, given that the mundane things exist, now that they don't, what is it that makes you get sullied by them?
[SPEAKER_05]: What is it that makes the lotus become sullied by the water, by the muddy water, yeah?
[SPEAKER_05]: Is it the things themselves?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, like you were saying before, passion towards people, desire and lust.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, it's that simple, really.
[SPEAKER_05]: Not understanding
[SPEAKER_05]: That things are not worthy of passion, you have passion towards them.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's the kind of beginningless state, as the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_05]: You cannot find a reason why passion is there.
[SPEAKER_05]: Just wherever you look, it's... it's gonna... you're gonna find that it's there already.
[SPEAKER_05]: You didn't create it.
[SPEAKER_05]: As a matter of choice, it's the fact that you have indirectly kind of generated it through your choices of rooted in passion.
[SPEAKER_05]: So,
[SPEAKER_05]: That's something that many people would understand.
[SPEAKER_05]: Like, you know, passion.
[SPEAKER_05]: The Buddha talks about giving up passion, aversion and delusion.
[SPEAKER_05]: And he says that nibbāna is the cessation of passion, aversion and delusion.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, just to pause here now for a minute.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you become attached to material things in the world, then you are giving power to things that are inherently powerless.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you can't now be without them.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's the foolishness of becoming attached to things in the world.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, seeing that you are stuck, you want to deny the reality of those things by saying that they are illusory.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whereas, actually, it is due to the wrong choices that you allowed yourself to become attached to them.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the issue.
[SPEAKER_02]: And our amount of denying the reality of those things
[SPEAKER_02]: That causes a problem.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, you make the house dirty and your solution is to demolish the whole thing.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because it's quicker, of course.
[SPEAKER_05]: But then, given that people know that, again, passion, aversion and delusion, that's like basic Buddhist dogma and, you know, has to be abandoned, and nibbāna is a cessation of those three things.
[SPEAKER_05]: Almost everybody knows that.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, if we're saying, well, that's what wisdom is, then somebody might say, well, I already know that, but I'm not enlightened yet.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, why is that?
[SPEAKER_05]: What is there that's missing?
[SPEAKER_04]: The cessation of those things.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, but...
[SPEAKER_05]: So, basically, let's say, how would they bring about the cessation of those things?
[SPEAKER_05]: If it's not through accessing some ultimate reality, if you kind of cannot help but be exposed to the same old, mundane, boring form, feeling, perception, intention, consciousness, then how can you, as the Sutta says, how can you kind of rise above all of that without then having to step into an alternate reality?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, so, I mean, it's...
[SPEAKER_05]: I think we'll probably repeat it in every single talk, but it's...
[SPEAKER_05]: The reason why the same knowledges and kind of, to some extent, intellectual information that you have,
[SPEAKER_05]: is not seen in such a way that it would free you from suffering, is because, yes, you know in principle that...
[SPEAKER_05]: Form is impermanent, suffering, not-self.
[SPEAKER_05]: But do you live as if that's the case?
[SPEAKER_05]: Or do you still act like someone who thinks that certain forms are pleasant, are permanent, and are yours?
[SPEAKER_05]: And it's as simple as that.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, you cannot, at the same time, expect that you will be... that that same information that you have will be sinking in.
[SPEAKER_05]: on the level that it must, for the passion to dissipate, if you continue to do the things that are fully rooted in that same passion.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, it's it's that simple.
[SPEAKER_05]: And then, if you were to actually go through, like, that's why when the Buddha would talk about the final discernment, like,
[SPEAKER_05]: To someone, for the first time, he wouldn't start by saying like, oh, yeah, nothing exists, it's impermanent and, you know, you just have to find that hidden reality and all your problems will be solved.
[SPEAKER_05]: He would say, no.
[SPEAKER_05]: First, a clansman hears the teaching, acquires faith,
[SPEAKER_05]: Then, they go forth.
[SPEAKER_05]: They take on the precepts, virtue, sense restraint, gives on the whole description of the reality of training, the work of purifying the mind from unwholesome states, and then, when the mind is sufficiently purified, they understand what?
[SPEAKER_05]: The ultimate reality?
[SPEAKER_05]: No.
[SPEAKER_05]: They understand suffering, the origin of suffering, the cessation of suffering, and the way that leads to the cessation of suffering.
[SPEAKER_05]: They understand
[SPEAKER_05]: The defilements, the origin of the defilements, the cessation of the defilements, and the way that leads to the cessation of the defilements.
[SPEAKER_05]: And then, once that's done, it says, there's nothing more to be done, being is destroyed, and they abide at ease until the aggregates break apart.
[SPEAKER_05]: So,
[SPEAKER_05]: That's the part that's missing, in other words.
[SPEAKER_05]: You have the information, you know that you've read about the Four Noble Truths, you have some recognition of the three characteristics, whichever aspect of the teaching you might want to
[SPEAKER_05]: To focus on, but you're not living in according to it, in accordance with it.
[SPEAKER_05]: You still live, and it says, the insight of a sotāpanna, everything that is liable to arise, is liable to cease.
[SPEAKER_05]: Now, you, again, like, look for some magical experience where you're going to get that insight.
[SPEAKER_05]: But, eh... what you actually have to look at... to see is, am I living in such a way that some things that are liable to arise, am I trying to not make... to make them never cease?
[SPEAKER_05]: Am I acting in such a way that I assume or hope that I could maintain some things?
[SPEAKER_02]: Or don't.
[SPEAKER_05]: You want to get rid of that.
[SPEAKER_05]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, because another one is like the whole ties in with this whole view of alternate reality and hidden perceptions is like the flux, like the constant change.
[SPEAKER_05]: Then, when you have something that makes you feel pain, you
[SPEAKER_05]: You conceive of the solution as being to tell yourself, oh, this will pass.
[SPEAKER_05]: This too shall pass.
[SPEAKER_05]: This is impermanent.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's all constantly changing.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's just molecules coming and going.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, either you deny the reality of it by saying it's constantly changing, therefore there's no essence, and it's all an illusion, failing to see that you actually still suffer.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's slightly a contradiction.
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, more accurately, like, if you had actually understood that it's liable to change, then why are you trying to get rid of it through that same, you know, supposedly right insight?
[SPEAKER_05]: But you realize, what is your attitude?
[SPEAKER_05]: What is your implied view there?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's like, no, no, actually, I'm not sure that it's going to pass away.
[SPEAKER_05]: So that's why I need to kind of... To do something about it.
[SPEAKER_05]: So to that extent, you are not rightly
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, and that's why you try to do any of these things, understand the impermanence, understand suffering, understand not-self, without having developed virtue, without having developed sensual strength, without having developed the prior training, you will be acting out of your single tendencies of impatience, of craving, of trying to get rid of things, and for that very reason alone, the the misconceiving of things as permanent,
[SPEAKER_05]: Misconceiving of craving... of not seeing even your own craving.
[SPEAKER_05]: All of that is still going to be there.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, that's why that's the that's the prerequisite.
[SPEAKER_05]: Even though it's not the dhamma, there is no dhamma without it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, so by... so, due to immense impatience, for example, which is rooted in the view that it will not go away,
[SPEAKER_02]: You actually... you keep reinforcing the view that those things are permanent and that that is where you should do something about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And as long as that's what you do, you're not gonna see that they are in fact impermanent.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the way to actually come to see things as impermanent, which does not mean that they are constantly changing, is ironically to endure those things which are real and are there enduring.
[SPEAKER_02]: Same with not-self.
[SPEAKER_05]: If you
[SPEAKER_05]: Like, it's quite amusing that sometimes the not-self idea would be re-explained as like, oh, it's empty of inherent essence.
[SPEAKER_05]: Meaning, like, again, another way of saying it doesn't really exist.
[SPEAKER_05]: And then, you're supposed to apply that view to everything you encounter, especially when it makes you suffer.
[SPEAKER_05]: And why is it that you're doing that?
[SPEAKER_05]: Because you're taking it personally.
[SPEAKER_05]: If you wouldn't be taking it personally, it wouldn't be making you suffer in the first place.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, you realize this is the level where these things have to be understood.
[SPEAKER_05]: On the level of, as we often say, the intention behind your action.
[SPEAKER_05]: Why am I doing this?
[SPEAKER_05]: That's where you will be holding all these assumptions and views.
[SPEAKER_03]: So...
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, it's something active that you're doing.
[SPEAKER_03]: All these methods are too late.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're already struck by suffering and you try to do something about it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, and it will only last for a limited amount of time.
[SPEAKER_05]: Whatever effect you get out of these, out of pasting these views over your experience, will only last a limited amount of time and that's why you need to keep renewing it.
[SPEAKER_05]: If you haven't done the formal meditation, where you access the ultimate reality again for a while, you will quickly find that, you know, you cannot actually over overrun the fact that pleasure and pain do arise.
[SPEAKER_05]: I might tell myself all I want, that it's not real, and there's this other dimension that's more real than it, but, eh... the the the kind of raw fact of
[SPEAKER_05]: Of it not actually caring about you, and what you think about it will reveal itself again.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: How do you know that the ultimate reality is not more painful?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, ultimately it is, because you realize the simple fact of needing to run away from things is precisely the reason why you're suffering.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, it's actually... and that's why the Buddha said there is right liberation and there is wrong liberation.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, even though these things might... you might get a sense that they're liberating you from the suffering, through that same liberation, you're inadvertently cultivating the same thing that gave rise to the problems in the end.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, you kind of... it's like a way of...
[SPEAKER_05]: Getting rid of the symptoms, a way that obscures the symptoms, while actually still making the actual illness worse.
[SPEAKER_05]: So then, whenever you stop, um, hiding those symptoms, you will probably find that the illness has actually become worse.
[SPEAKER_05]: And that's why... what often happens, like, when you become... when you find safety in these... these kind of higher perceptions or whatever, and... and then you don't get to do it for a while, you will see that
[SPEAKER_05]: Things actually affect you twice as much, because you've been cultivating weakness by running away from it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, because why would you restrain yourself and question your greed, hatred and illusion, if you still assume that the solution is finding this ultimate reality?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's a wrong view, but also it prevents you from actually seeing what the real work is.
[SPEAKER_05]: That will also exactly happen.
[SPEAKER_05]: Like, that's why then, yeah, the whole
[SPEAKER_05]: Only for as long as I still haven't achieved this higher reality, and once I do, all of this becomes secondary, because it was never real to begin with.
[SPEAKER_05]: So...
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's what makes it a wrong view.
[SPEAKER_02]: The fact that it doesn't lead to freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like it's a wrong view because it's false and it also doesn't happen to lead to freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is the benchmark for... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, it doesn't lead...
[SPEAKER_05]: It might lead to removing the causes of suffering.
[SPEAKER_05]: It might remove... that's why I said, like, the symptoms and the illness.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, the symptoms of you actually experiencing pleasant feelings at that time, you can suppress that.
[SPEAKER_05]: But mind you, you don't need the Buddha for that.
[SPEAKER_05]: You can do that in a million different ways.
[SPEAKER_05]: But the cause, which is a craving,
[SPEAKER_05]: The same thing that you're still cultivating toward these higher realities, that's still there.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's just that kind of... it will have a delayed effect.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, it will catch up on you later on.
[SPEAKER_05]: It won't be apparent right then and there.
[SPEAKER_05]: That same attitude that you're cultivating toward these things is what generated the same suffering that you were running away from in the past.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's the same with saṃsāra, actually.
[SPEAKER_05]: In the moment, it feels like it's great.
[SPEAKER_05]: Only afterwards, when you're kind of cut away from that which you were welcoming, you realize the suffering that you've... the liability to suffering that you've been feeding.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, you create that dependence on something that's higher, and now that higher thing becomes your addiction, becomes that which you need to maintain.
[SPEAKER_05]: And that's why the Buddha said,
[SPEAKER_05]: The one who gives things up rightly, he does so without taking up something new.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, because somebody might have an idea of some higher or ultimate reality, and in order to go there, they might in fact abandon a whole bunch of, let's say, other attachments or lower things, but still... For the wrong reason.
[SPEAKER_02]: For the wrong reason.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, they can...
[SPEAKER_05]: Replacing one craving with a more subtle craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, but what we are now saying is that all of that giving up still needs to happen,
[SPEAKER_02]: But in the absence of you going somewhere else, basically.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, and that's what's going to make it, as you said, it's going to make it more boring, because you realize, yeah, I'm not going to get some magical reward out of this.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's just, I will have the same things, but...
[SPEAKER_05]: I won't suffer anymore.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: And that doesn't sound as exhilarating.
[SPEAKER_05]: But well, that's that's how life is.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's it's it's the things that are shiny and pleasant and quick fixes are usually just gimmicks.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's much more challenging as well.
[SPEAKER_03]: I could listen to this and think I need to
[SPEAKER_03]: I need to tighten up my restraint.
[SPEAKER_03]: I need to start giving things up.
[SPEAKER_03]: I need to see the danger, not just this gratification.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, I need to see...
[SPEAKER_03]: I need to see a rope as a snake, instead of a snake as a rope.
[SPEAKER_03]: And so, I just replace the beautiful with, like, the ugly.
[SPEAKER_03]: And I just deny that aspect.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, thinking I'm practicing mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, actually, that's another thing I wanted to go back to.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, the right type of wisdom, since that's what we started to talk with, is not that the snake, the rope, is not a snake.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's that even when it is a snake, and it's actually a poisonous viper, and it's actually biting you right in the neck, you don't suffer.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's what the wisdom is.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's not that, oh, this is not what it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, that would be the goal of the practice, I think.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's what your understanding is measured by.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's not how much you can pretend that things are not what they are, or make them appear otherwise.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's how, when the worst case scenario comes,
[SPEAKER_05]: And you cannot escape from it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: You cannot go left, right, up or down, front or back.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, the question is, has the work been done or not?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: And there was one more sutta that I wanted to read, to eh...
[SPEAKER_05]: So, it says that the the eight worldly phenomena, loka-dhamma, so that's another common teaching that appears in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_05]: It says, because the eight worldly phenomena follow the world around, and the world follows the eight worldly phenomena around.
[SPEAKER_05]: What eight?
[SPEAKER_05]: Gain and loss,
[SPEAKER_05]: of ultimate realities, uh, honor and dishonor, blame and praise, pleasure and displeasure.
[SPEAKER_05]: These eight worldly phenomena follow the world around, and the world follows the eight worldly phenomena around.
[SPEAKER_05]: For an unlearned ordinary person, gain and loss, honor and dishonor, blame and praise, and pleasure and displeasure arise.
[SPEAKER_05]: And so do they for a learned and noble disciple.
[SPEAKER_05]: What, then, is the difference between a learned noble cycle and an ordinary unlearned person?
[SPEAKER_05]: So, that's what we were saying before, like, if it's just about these same mundane things, what is it that you don't understand?
[SPEAKER_05]: And so, it says, because gain arises for an unlearned ordinary person, they don't reflect.
[SPEAKER_05]: This gain has arisen for me.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's impermanent, suffering, imperishable.
[SPEAKER_05]: They don't understand it as it is.
[SPEAKER_05]: Loss arises.
[SPEAKER_05]: Honor, dishonor, blame, praise, displeasure, uh, pleasure, displeasure, uh, arise.
[SPEAKER_05]: Uh, they don't reflect.
[SPEAKER_05]: This displeasure has arisen for me.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's impermanent, suffering, imperishable.
[SPEAKER_05]: They don't understand it as it is.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, gain and loss, honor and dishonor, blame and praise, and pleasure and displeasure, endure with a grip on their mind.
[SPEAKER_05]: They embrace gain and resist loss.
[SPEAKER_05]: They embrace fame and resist disgrace.
[SPEAKER_05]: They embrace praise and oppose blame.
[SPEAKER_05]: They embrace pleasure and oppose displeasure.
[SPEAKER_05]: Being thus engaged in embracing embracing and resisting, they're not freed from birth, aging, and death, from sorrow, lamentation, displeasure, sadness, and distress.
[SPEAKER_05]: They're not freed from suffering, I say.
[SPEAKER_05]: Now, because gain arises for a learned noble disciple, they do reflect.
[SPEAKER_05]: This gain has arisen for me.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's impermanent, suffering, and perishable.
[SPEAKER_05]: They understand it as it is.
[SPEAKER_05]: Loss, honor, dishonor, blame, praise, pleasure, displeasure.
[SPEAKER_05]: They reflect.
[SPEAKER_05]: This pleasure has arisen for me.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's impermanent, suffering, and perishable.
[SPEAKER_05]: They understand it as it is.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, when gain and loss, honor and dishonor, blame and praise, and pleasure and displeasure,
[SPEAKER_05]: Arise, they don't endure with a grip on their mind.
[SPEAKER_05]: They don't embrace gain or resist loss.
[SPEAKER_05]: They don't embrace honor or resist dishonor.
[SPEAKER_05]: They don't embrace praise or resist blame.
[SPEAKER_05]: They don't embrace pleasure or resist displeasure.
[SPEAKER_05]: Having given up embracing and resisting, they're freed from birth, aging, and death, from sorrow, lamentations, pleasure, sadness, and distress.
[SPEAKER_05]: They're freed from suffering, I say.
[SPEAKER_05]: And then, it ends with a...
[SPEAKER_05]: This is the difference between a learned noble disciple and an unlearned ordinary person.
[SPEAKER_05]: And then, it finishes with a verse.
[SPEAKER_05]: Gain and loss, honor and dishonor, blame and praise, and pleasure and displeasure, these qualities among people are impermanent, transient, and perishable.
[SPEAKER_05]: An intelligent and mindful person, having known these things, sees that they're perishable.
[SPEAKER_05]: Pleasing phenomena don't disturb their mind, nor do they harbor resistance against the undesirable.
[SPEAKER_05]: Both embracing and resisting are dispelled and ended.
[SPEAKER_05]: They are no more.
[SPEAKER_05]: Knowing the stainless, sorrowless state, they, gone beyond being, understand rightly.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, the stainless sore of the state being cessation of passion.
[SPEAKER_05]: Cessation of complete cooling down, nibbāna, of passion and aversion and ignorance, in regard to
[SPEAKER_05]: The eight worldly things that you cannot escape from, even if you want to.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, a noble disciple understands the right gain has come to me, but it's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that gain is real, but it's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: He does not say
[SPEAKER_02]: That game is impermanent, therefore it's not real.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, that game is real and it is impermanent and that's precisely what he has understood.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, rather than denying the game, what he sees is the danger in now becoming infatuated with that game, because it's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_05]: See, it's much more, in a sense, mundane, but as you said before, the reason why it's not as attractive
[SPEAKER_05]: It is because it reveals this whole additional dimension of work that you have to do.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: Not things that will just sort themselves out by just seeing them.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, ultimately, the reality is for those who are lazy.
[SPEAKER_03]: And it's your responsibility.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: The responsibility that, yeah, it's... Shame.
[SPEAKER_05]: Not because I'm just not fortunate that I haven't discovered this yet, even though I've been practicing for 20 years.
[SPEAKER_05]: If you're still suffering, it's because, on some level, you must still be fueling the fire of passion.
[SPEAKER_05]: There's no other explanation for it.